<section><title>The OfxHost Struct</title>
  <para>The <structname>OfxHost</structname> struct is how a host
    provides plug-ins with access to the various suites that make up the
    API they implement, as well as a host property set handle which a plug-in can ask
    questions of. The <function>setHost</function> function in the
    <structname>OfxPlugin</structname> struct is passed a pointer to an
    <structname>OfxHost</structname> as the first thing to boot-strapping
    plug-in/host communication. The struct looks like...</para>
  <programlisting>
typedef struct OfxHost {
  OfxPropertySetHandle host;
  void *(*fetchSuite)(OfxPropertySetHandle host, const char *suiteName, int suiteVersion);
} OfxHost;
  </programlisting>

  <para>The <structname>OfxHost</structname> contains two elements,
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem> <structfield>host</structfield> - a property set handle that holds a set of properties which describe the host for the plug-in's API </listitem> <listitem> <structfield>fetchSuite</structfield> - a function handle used to fetch function suites from the host that implement the plug-in's API </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  
  <para>The <structfield>host</structfield> property set handle in the
    <structname>OfxHost</structname> is not global across all plug-ins
    defined in the binary. It is only applicable for the plug-in whose
    'setHost' function was called. Use this handle to fetch things like
    host application names, host capabilities and so on from. The set of
    properties on an OFX Image Effect host is found in the section <link linkend="ImageEffectHostProperties">Properties on the Image Effect Host</link>
  </para>
  
  <para>The <function>fetchSuite</function> function is how a plug-in
    gets a suite from the host. It asks for a suite by giving the cstring
    corresponding to that suite and the version of that suite. The host
    will return a pointer to that suite, or NULL if it does not support
    it. Please note that suite cannot be fetched until the very first
    action is called on the plug-in. Which is the load action.</para>
 </section>
