<section>
  <title id="InstallationLocation">Packaging OFX Plug-ins</title>
  
  <para>Where a host application chooses to search for OFX plug ins, what
    binary format they are in and any directory hierarchy is entirely up to
    it. However, it is strongly recommended that the following scheme be
    followed.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Binary Types</title>
    
    <para>Plug-ins should be distributed in the following formats,
      depending on the host operating system.... <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  Microsoft Windows, as ".dll" dynamically linked libraries, 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  Apple OSX, as Mach-O binary bundles, 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  IRIX and LINUX, as ELF dynamic shared objects. 
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Installation Directory Hierarchy</title>
    
    <para>Each plug-in binary is distributed as a Mac OS X package style
      directory hierarchy. Note that the there are two distinct meanings of
      'bundle', one referring to a binary file format, the other to a
      directory hierarchy used to distribute software. We are distributing
      binaries in a bundle package, and in the case of OSX, the binary is a
      binary bundle. All the binaries must end with
      <literal>".ofx"</literal>, regardless of the host operating
      system.</para>
    
    <para>The directory hierarchy is as follows..... 
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>NAME.ofx.bundle
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>Contents
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>Info.plist</listitem>
		<listitem>Resources
		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>NAME.xml</listitem>
		    <listitem>PLUGIN_A.png</listitem>
		    <listitem>PLUGIN_B.png</listitem>
		    <listitem>...</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>ARCHITECTURE_A <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>NAME.ofx</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist></listitem>
		
		<listitem>ARCHITECTURE_B <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>NAME.ofx</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist></listitem>
		
		<listitem>...</listitem>
		
		<listitem>ARCHITECTURE_N <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>NAME.ofx</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist></listitem>
		
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      
      Where... <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  Info.plist is relevant for OSX only and needs to be filled in appropriately, 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  NAME is the file name you want the installed plug-in to be identified by, 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  PLUGIN.png - is the image to use as an icon for the plug-in in the binary which has a matching 
	  
	  <structfield>pluginIdentifier</structfield>
	  
	  field in the 
	  
	  <structname>OfxPlugin</structname>
	  
	  struct, 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  ARCHITECTURE is the specific operating system architecture the plug-in was built for, these are currently... 
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>MacOS - for Apple Macintosh OS X (compiled 32
	      bit)</listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>Win32 - for Microsoft Windows (compiled 32
	      bit)</listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>IRIX - for SGI IRIX plug-ins (compiled 32
	      bit)</listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>IRIX64 - for SGI IRIX plug-ins (compiled 64
	      bit)</listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>Linux-x86 - for Linux on intel x86 CPUs (compiled 32
	      bit)</listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>Linux-x86-64 - for Linux on intel x86 CPUs running
	      AMD's 64 bit extensions</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist> Note that not all the above architectures need be
      supported, at least one.</para>
    
    <para>This structure is necessary on OS X, but it also gives a nice
      skeleton to hang all other operating systems from in a single install,
      as well as a clean place to put resources.</para>
    
    <para>The <filename>Info.plist</filename> is specific to Apple and you
      should consult the Apple developer's website for more details. It
      should contain the following keys... <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  CFBundleExecutable - the name of the binary bundle in the MacOS directory 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  CFBundlePackageType - to be 'BNDL' 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  CFBundleInfoDictionaryVersion 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  CFBundleVersion 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  CFBundleDevelopmentRegion 
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ArchitectureInstallingLocation">
    <title>Installation Location</title>
    
    <para>Plug ins are searched for in a variety of locations, both
      default and user specified. All such directories are examined for
      plug-in bundles and sub directories are also recursively
      examined.</para>
    
    <para>A list of directories is supplied in the "OFX_PLUGIN_PATH"
      environment variable, these are examined, first to last, for plug ins,
      then the default location is examined.</para>
    
    <para>
      On Microsoft Windows machines, the plug ins are searched for in,
<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  the ';' separated directory list specified by the environment variable "OFX_PLUGIN_PATH"
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>

	  the directory returned by <code>getStdOFXPluginPath</code> in the following code snippet...
	      <programlisting>
#include "shlobj.h"
#include "tchar.h"
const TCHAR *getStdOFXPluginPath(void)
{
  static TCHAR buffer[MAX_PATH];
  static int gotIt = 0;
  if(!gotIt) {
    gotIt = 1;	   
    SHGetFolderPath(NULL, CSIDL_PROGRAM_FILES_COMMON, NULL, SHGFP_TYPE_CURRENT, buffer);
    _tcscat(buffer, __T("\\OFX\\Plugins"));
  }
  return buffer;	   
}
	      </programlisting>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  the directory "C:\Program Files\Common Files\OFX\Plugins". This location is deprecated, and it is returned by the code snippet above on English language systems. However it should still be examined by hosts for backwards compatibility.
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      On Apple OSX machines, the plug ins are searched for
      in, <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  the ';' separated directory list specified by the environment variable "OFX_PLUGIN_PATH" 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  the directory "/Library/OFX/Plugins" 
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist> On UNIX, Linux and other UNIX like operating systems,
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  the ':' separated directory specified by the environment variable "OFX_PLUGIN_PATH" 
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  the directory "/usr/OFX/Plugins" 
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
    
    <para>Any bundle or sub-directory name starting with the character '@'
      is to be ignored. Such directories or bundles must be skipped.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Plug-in Icons</title>
    
    <para>Some hosts may wish to display an icon associated with a plug-in
      on their interfaces. Any such icon must be in the Portable Network
      Graphics format (see http://www.libpng.org/) and must contain 32 bits
      of colour, including an alpha channel. Ideally it should be at least
      128x128 pixels.</para>
    
    <para>Host applications should dynamically resize the icon to fit
      their preferred icon size. The icon should not have it's aspect
      changed, rather the host should fill with some appropriate colour any
      blank areas due to aspect mis matches.</para>
    
    <para>Ideally plug-in developers should not render the plug-in's name
      into the icon, as this may be changed by the resource file, especially
      for internationalisation purposes. Hosts should thus present the
      plug-in's name next to the icon in some way.</para>
    
    <para>The icon file must be named as the corresponding
      <structfield>pluginIdentifier</structfield> field from the
      <structname>OfxPlugin</structname>, post pended with '.png' and be
      placed in the resources sub-directory.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Externally Specified Resources</title>
    
    <para>Some plug-ins may supply an externally specified resource file.
      Typically this is for tasks such as internationalising interfaces,
      tweaking user interfaces for specific hosts and so on. These are XML
      files and have DTD associated with the specific API, for example OFX
      Image Effect DTD is found in <filename>ofx.dtd</filename>.</para>
    
    <para>The xml resource file is installed in the
      <filename>Resources</filename> sub directory of the bundle hierarchy.
      It's name will be <filename>NAME.xml</filename>, where name is the
      base name of the bundle folder and the effect binaries.</para>
  </section>
 </section>
